Guide to the Claire Yaffa Children with Aids Photographs 1987-2010 (bulk 1990-2000) PR 290
New-York Historical Society
Claire Yaffa Children With Aids photographs
1987-2010 (bulk 1990-2000)
New-York Historical Society
Yaffa, Claire
PR 290
2.67 Linear feet (5 boxes, 7 flat folders)
This collection consists of photographs by Claire Yaffa of children with AIDS, taken over a ten-year period at the Incarnation Children's Hospital in the Bronx. Also included are a series of 1991 photographs of the potter's field on Hart Island, where many of these children are buried.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Claire Yaffa, 2012.
Access restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of photographs and documents from a series Yaffa began in 1990 documenting children with AIDs at the Incarnation Children's Center ("ICC") in the Bronx.
In the mid-1980's, a growing number of children with HIV/AIDs were abandoned, orphaned, or removed from their parents because of drug use, neglect or abuse. The foster care system, already overburdened with crack cocaine babies, was unable to find foster parents willing to care for these children. As a result, these so-called "boarder babies," who had nowhere else to live, languished in New York City's hospital wards and in many cases died before foster homes became available.
In response to these conditions, ICC opened in 1989 as a hybrid medical/foster care facility for children born with AIDs. Housed in a four-story red brick former convent in upper Manhattan, ICC provided a homelike residence for HIV-positive children until they were placed in foster homes, or for some of the sickest children, until they died.
Claire Yaffa began photographing the children and staff at ICC in 1990 and continued to document them over the next decade. Exhibitions of this work were mounted at Sarah Lawrence College, the Cleveland Museum of Health and Science, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Neuberger Museum, and Fait et Cause in Paris, France. Yaffa also produced a monograph documenting the 13 month life span of a child born prematurely with the AIDS virus and abandoned by her mother, titled "A Dying Child is Born."
The bulk of the photographs in this collection are portraits of individual children treated at ICC, very few of whom survived. Often they are shown with the staff and volunteers who cared for them. Also included are a series of photographs taken at Camp Compass, a week long retreat in 1995 for children treated at ICC, and at the potter's field on Hart Island, where many of the children treated at ICC were buried. While the majority of the photographs are gelatin silver prints, there are also some color snapshots. Numerous contact sheets include many images that were not printed, providing a more comprehensive view of ICC activities.
The collection also includes one box of documents pertaining to ICC, exhibitions of Yaffa's photographs, and children with AIDS generally.
Biographical / Historical
Claire Yaffa is a freelance photographer, noted for her social realism. Her photographs portray society's less fortunate -- the homeless, the aging, the handicapped -- and focus especially on the problems of child abuse and neglect. Her work has been exhibited at the Hudson River Museum, the International Center of Photography, Sarah Lawrence College, the White Plains Museum Gallery, the United Nations, and other galleries throughout America.
Yaffa's photographs have been published in The New York Times, The Daily News, Vanity Fair, and Vogue. She has photographed for a variety of medical organizations including the National Foundation for Children with Learning Disabilities, Bronx Lebanon Hospital and Columbia-Presbyterian Hospital. She has also published two monographs of her reportage work: Reaching Out (1987) and A Dying Child is Born: The Story of Tracy (1992).
More recently, Yaffa has changed her focus from photojournalism to more poetic subjects. Her work has been published by Ruder Finn Press in three monographs, described as a series of visual poems: Moments (2004), Life's Dream (2006), and Divertissement... I Dreamed a Dream (2008).
In addition to taking pictures, Yaffa has served as photography editor of Westchester Magazine and photography coordinator of the United Nations Women's Arts Festival. She has also served on the Board of Directors of ICP's Archival and Acquisition Committee. In 1995, she received the Westchester Arts Council Award.
Arrangement
This collection has been organized into the following three series:
Series I: Photographs
Series II: Contact sheets
Series III: Documents
Related Materials at the New-York Historical Society
Claire Yaffa New York Foundling Hospital Photograph Collection 1979-2012 (bulk 1979-1999)
Abandoned children -- New York (State) -- New York.; AIDS (disease); Incarnation Children's Center (Bronx, N.Y.) -- Photographs.
- Series I: Photographic prints
  - Tracy/A Dying Child is Born, 1990 - 1991 (Offsite-box 1A, Folder 1)
  - Tracy/A Dying Child is Born, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - Anthony V., 1990 - 1992 (Offsite-box 1A, Folder 2)
  - Anthony V., 1990-1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Anthony V., 1990-1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Devonne, 1990 - 1999 (Offsite-box 1A, Folder 3)
  - Devonne, 1990-1999 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gilbert, 1990 - 1991 (Offsite-box 1B, Folder 4)
  - Gilbert, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Aisha, undated (Offsite-box 1B, Folder 5)
  - Angelica, 1990, undated (Offsite-box 1B, Folder 6)
  - Angelica, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Annette G., undated (Offsite-box 1B, Folder 7)
  - Annette S., undated (Offsite-box 1B, Folder 8)
  - Annette S. (color snapshots), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Anthony, undated (Offsite-box 1B, Folder 9)
  - Anthony, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Brenda, undated (Offsite-box 1B, Folder 10)
  - Brenda, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - Donald, undated (Offsite-box 1B, Folder 11)
  - Donald, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - James, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - Josephine, undated (Offsite-box 1B, Folder 12)
  - Josephine, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - Karen, undated (Offsite-box 1B, Folder 13)
  - Karen, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
  - Natalie, undated (Offsite-box 1C, Folder 14)
  - Natalie, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
  - Trevaris, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
  - Vincent, undated (Offsite-box 1C, Folder 15)
  - Identified children (exhibition prints), undated (Box Flat files, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified girls, undated (Offsite-box 1C, Folder 16)
  - Unidentified girls, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
  - Unidentified boys, undated (Offsite-box 1C, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified boys, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified children (exhibition prints), undated (Box Flat files, Folder 2)
  - Group shots at ICC, undated (Offsite-box 1C, Folder 18)
  - Group shots at ICC, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
  - Group shots at ICC (color snapshots), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
  - Caregivers (women), undated (Offsite-box 1C, Folder 19)
  - Caregivers (women)(includes color snapshots), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  - Caregivers (men), undated (Offsite-box 1D, Folder 20)
  - Caregivers (men), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
  - Caregivers (exhibition prints), undated (Box Flat files, Folder 3)
  - Hands, undated (Offsite-box 1D, Folder 21)
  - Hands, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
  - Hands (exhibition prints), undated (Box Flat files, Folder 4)
  - Medical treatment, undated (Offsite-box 1D, Folder 22)
  - Medical treatment, undated (Offsite-box 1D, Folder 23)
  - Medical treatment, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
  - Medical treatment (exhibition prints), undated (Box Flat files, Folder 5)
  - Dr. Nicholas, undated (Offsite-box 1D, Folder 24)
  - Dr. Nicholas (includes color snapshots), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
  - Camp Compass, 1995 (Offsite-box 1D, Folder 25)
  - Camp Compass (color snapshots), 1995 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  - Memorial services, undated (Offsite-box 1D, Folder 26)
  - Memorial services, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
  - Exhibitions (color snapshots) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
  - Quilts (color slides), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  - Potter's field, Hart Island, 1991 (Box Flat files, Folder 6)
- Series II: Contact sheets, 1989-2000
  - Contact sheets, 1989-2000 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-5)
  - Mock-up boards, 1991 April - 1996 March, undated (Box Flat files, Folder 7)
- Series III: Documents
  - Correspondence, bills and receipts, 1990 October - 2002 July, 2011 April 20, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Claire Yaffa biographical material and proposals, 1998, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Incarnation Children's Center, 1990 - 2000, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
  - Profiles of children, interviews and memorial services, 1988 September 28 - 2000 February, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
  - Dr. Stephen Nicholas, 1990 March - 2010 June (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - Camp Compass, 1995 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
  - Exhibit, A Dying Child Is Born, 1992 October - 1994 January, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
  - Exhibit, Children with AIDS: An Endangered Species, 1993 July - 1994 May, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
  - Exhibit, Un conte de vie et de mort, 2002 April - August, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
  - Articles about AIDs/children, 1987 April - 2009 June, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - Potter's Field, Hart Island, 1987 September - 2010 October, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)